<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 | Academic</title>
    <link>/publication_types/2/</link>
      <atom:link href="/publication_types/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>2</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>/publication_types/2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>An introduction to Sequence Analysis</title>
      <link>/project/project_1_sabook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/project_1_sabook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How does the school-to-work transition process look like in different countries? Do individual electoral participation pattern differ across context with varying degrees of residential segregation? How similar are employment biographies across cohorts of workers who entered the labor market before and after the recent economic crisis? Do democratization processes differ depending on the pathways of turnover between rightist and leftist parties? Answering these research questions requires the application of analysis tools that capture how processes unfold over time. Within the toolkit of longitudinal methods, we consider social sequence analysis to be one of the most powerful and versatile ones – particularly when it comes to studying longitudinal categorical data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sequence analysis was introduced in the social sciences in the 1980s. Andrew Abbott, inspired by the treatment of DNA strings in biology, developed it as a technique to study social processes that unfold over time as sequences of events (Abbott &amp;amp; Forrest, 1986). Sequence analysis has gained increasing attention as the recent widespread availability of longitudinal data made it possible to address sequence-oriented questions. The mainstream application of sequence analysis relies on optimal matching techniques to measure the distance between sequences that represent the individual realization of a certain process and on the clustering of such sequences to identify typical trajectories. Regression analysis is often applied as a second step to investigate why (and not only how) sequences resemble or differ from each other. In the last ten years, several innovations have been introduced to overcome weaknesses and limitation of the initial proposition. A sequence analysis introductory book is currently missing in the QASS series. Therefore, the book will complement the rich catalogue of the QASS series with an up-to-date introduction to a technique that is steadily gaining popularity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several statistical software tools made it available to a broader public. However, existing publications on sequence analysis that might serve the purpose of teaching and learning its basics, are scattered across several journal articles, books, and software documentations. This makes it hard for newcomers to figure out where to start and to identify good practices for performing methodologically sound analyses. To answer these needs, the book introduces the basics of sequence analysis to guide practitioners and support instructors along the working flow of sequence analysis. The presentation of statistical, substantive, and theoretical foundations will be enriched by examples to help the reader in understanding the advantages and disadvantages of specific analytical choices. The extensive ancillary material will support self-learning by offering exercises and solutions based on real data and research questions in the field of life course research. Finally, the book will include practical guidelines considering recent advances and innovations in sequence analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being working poor or feeling working poor? The role of work intensity and job stability for subjective poverty</title>
      <link>/publication/filandripasquastruffolino2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/filandripasquastruffolino2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Navigating the early career. The social stratification of young workers&#39; employment trajectories in Italy</title>
      <link>/publication/struffolino2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/struffolino2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heuristics for validation and visualization in Sequence Analysis</title>
      <link>/project/project_4_methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/project_4_methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Publications in progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Piccarreta R., Struffolino E., &lt;em&gt;Heuristics for validation in Sequence Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Piccarreta R., Struffolino E., &lt;em&gt;Enhancing fuzzy clusters’ interpretation  through visualization&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lavoro e salute. L’importanza di considerare le traiettorie di carriera [Work and health. The importance of employment trajetories]</title>
      <link>/dissemination/devillaraitanostruffolino2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/devillaraitanostruffolino2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outreach on &lt;em&gt;Neodemos.info&lt;/em&gt; of the article &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Multiple life-course employment trajectories and health. Evidence from linked administrative and survey data&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Individual and household in-work poverty in Europe. understanding the role of labor market characteristics</title>
      <link>/publication/filandristruffolino2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/filandristruffolino2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple life-course employment trajectories and health. Evidence from linked administrative and survey data</title>
      <link>/publication/devillanovaraitanostruffolino2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/devillanovaraitanostruffolino2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wege aus der Erwerbsarmut in den USA [Pathways out of in-work poverty in the US]</title>
      <link>/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Published in the &lt;em&gt;WZB-Mitteilungen Nr. 164&lt;/em&gt;, in the special issue &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Es wird eng. Ein Heft über die Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Heterogeneity of Partnership Trajectories to Childlessness in Germany</title>
      <link>/publication/raabstruffolino2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/raabstruffolino2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lavoratrici ma povere [Women who work but are poor]</title>
      <link>/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outreach published on &lt;em&gt;InGenere.it - Dati, Politiche, Questioni di Genere&lt;/em&gt; of the article &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;When working isn&amp;rsquo;t enough. Family Demographic Process and In-Work Poverty across the Life Course in the United States&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Family Demographic Processes and In-Work Poverty in Europe</title>
      <link>/project/project_2_oxber/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/project_2_oxber/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project analyses the role of family demographic processes (leaving parental home, marriage, divorce, and parenthood) for the probability of being working poor and how it changes over the life course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publications in progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struffolino E., Van Winkle Z., Family formation and union dissolution and in-work poverty: Gender differences across the life course in comparative perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struffolino E., Van Winkle Z., Polizzi A., Family-demographic processes and in-work poverty: A systematic review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Van Winkle Z., Struffolino E., Parity and in-work poverty across the life course in comparative perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is funded by the &lt;em&gt;Oxford/Berlin Research Partnership - 2018&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perchè il ddl Pillon non è una buona idea [Why the Pillon-Law proposal on mantainance after separation is not a good idea]</title>
      <link>/dissemination/larenzastruffolino2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/larenzastruffolino2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;published on &lt;em&gt;InGenere.it - Dati, Politiche, Questioni di Genere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender differences in early school leaving. Academic performance, family resources, and labor-market opportunities.</title>
      <link>/project/project_3_it_drop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/project_3_it_drop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given the rising skill demands of the labor market, early school leavers constitute a vulnerable group in contemporary societies: young people who do not hold any kind of upper-secondary qualification tend to experience difficulties in transitioning to the first job and in later labor market integration. Early school leaving is also connected to other negative outcomes such as poor health and lack of civic and political participation. From a policy perspective, early school leaving can therefore be considered a “new social risk”, as recognized by the EU strategy for growth for which the reduction of early school leaving to less than 10% is one of the main five targets to be met until the year 2020.
Not only is early school leaving connected to negative labor market outcomes, but it also tends to hit the social groups that are most vulnerable in terms of labor market integration: children with learning difficulties, coming from socio-economically disadvantaged families or who have access to limited educational resources. Hence, early school leaving exacerbates social inequalities.
When it comes to gender, however, the definition of a vulnerable group may prove elusive, because while women still face labor market disadvantages in most industrialized societies, in terms of educational attainment they have caught up to men and, in many countries, even overtaken them.
Together with Portugal and Spain, Italy is one of the EU countries with the greatest proportion of early school leavers. In this country, early school leaving has been steadily declining since the 1990s, when it reached percentages of 30% or more. However, as of today still 15% of young Italians leave education and training before completing the upper-secondary cycle. This phenomenon is therefore alarming, especially if we consider the increasing difficulties that Italian youth is facing in labor-market entry: it suffices to say that as of 2015 the youth unemployment rate reached 40%.
Moreover, in Italy, gender disparities are particularly strong: on the one hand, women’s participation to the labor market is very low and, even among the young cohorts, the women who work are more likely than men to have atypical and poorly-paid jobs. On the other hand, the gender gap is reversed when it comes to education: young women outnumber men by three to two among tertiary graduates and boys are vastly overrepresented among the pupils who do not reach a basic level of competences in core subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publications in progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Struffolino E., Borgna C., Who is really left behind? Gender differences in the school-to-work transition of
low-skilled youth in Italy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Borgna, C., Struffolino E., Tempi difficili. Le condizioni occupazionali degli early school
leavers in Italia prima e dopo la crisi [Hard times. Labor-market outcomes of early school leavers in Italy
before and after the crisis]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Working Isn’t Enough. Family Demographic Process and In-Work Poverty across the Life Course in the United States</title>
      <link>/publication/vanwinklestruffolino2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/vanwinklestruffolino2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the Relationship between Time-varying Covariates and Trajectories. The Sequence Analysis Multistate Model Procedure</title>
      <link>/publication/studerstruffolinofasang2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/studerstruffolinofasang2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Il generation gap nell&#39;accesso al mercato del lavoro. Complessità e destandardizzazione delle traiettorie di ingresso</title>
      <link>/publication/struffolinoraitano2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/struffolinoraitano2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lavoratori o lavoratrici povere? Disuguaglianze di genere nel mercato del lavoro in Europa.</title>
      <link>/publication/filandristruffolino2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/filandristruffolino2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lone mothers in Belgium. Labour force attachment and risk factors.</title>
      <link>/publication/struffolinomortelmans2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/struffolinomortelmans2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrant Status and Lone Motherhood. Risk Factors of Female Labour Force Participation in Switzerland.</title>
      <link>/publication/milewskistruffolinobernardi2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/milewskistruffolinobernardi2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unpacking configurational dynamics. Sequence analysis and qualitative comparative analysis as a mixed-method design</title>
      <link>/publication/borgnastruffolino2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/borgnastruffolino2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The stratification of contraceptive use at first intercourse in Italy, 1950-2006</title>
      <link>/project/project_5_contraception/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/project_5_contraception/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender, education, and family life courses in East and West Germany. Insights from new sequence analysis techniques</title>
      <link>/publication/studerstruffolinofasang2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/studerstruffolinofasang2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schule und das Push’n Pull. Vorzeitiger Schulabgang unter Mädchen und Jungen in Italien</title>
      <link>/dissemination/borgnastruffolino2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/borgnastruffolino2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outreach on &lt;em&gt;WZB - Mitteilungen&lt;/em&gt; issue N. 155 &lt;em&gt;“Digital Wie Arbeit, Leben, Forschung sich und uns verändern”&lt;/em&gt; of the article &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pushed or pulled? Girls and boys facing early school leaving risk in Italy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vulnerabilität alleinerziehender Mütter in der Schweiz aus einer Lebensverlaufsperspektive</title>
      <link>/publication/struffolinobernardi2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/struffolinobernardi2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pushed or pulled? Girls and boys facing early school leaving risk in Italy</title>
      <link>/publication/borgnastruffolino2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/borgnastruffolino2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mehrfach benachteiligt. Wie Bildung, Job und Einkommen die Gesundheit alleinerziehender Mütter in der Schweiz prägen</title>
      <link>/dissemination/struffolino2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/struffolino2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outreach published on &lt;em&gt;WZB - Mitteilungen&lt;/em&gt; N. 153 &amp;ldquo;Familie 2016. Arbeit, Gesundheit und Partnerschaft im Kontext.&amp;rdquo; of the article &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Self-reported health among lone mothers in Switzerland. Do employment and education matter?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One-parent households in Switzerland. Continuity and change over time.</title>
      <link>/dissemination/struffolinobernardi2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/struffolinobernardi2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Publiches in &lt;em&gt;Demos - Demographic information&lt;/em&gt;, ”Family, migration” - No. 1 June 2016 , Neuchâtel: Swiss Federal Statistical Office.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-reported health among lone mothers in Switzerland. Do employment and education matter?</title>
      <link>/publication/struffolinobernardivoorpostel2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/struffolinobernardivoorpostel2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>L’abbandono scolastico in Italia. Genere, risorse familiari e mercato del lavoro [Early school-leaving in Itay. Gender, family background, and the labour market].</title>
      <link>/dissemination/borgnastruffolino2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/borgnastruffolino2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Published on &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Menabò di Etica &amp;amp; Economia&lt;/em&gt;, eticaeconomia.it&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Così uguali, così diversi [So much alike, but so unequal].</title>
      <link>/dissemination/borgnaetal2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/borgnaetal2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Published on nelMerito.com.  1.10.2015.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example journal article</title>
      <link>/cv/journal-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/cv/journal-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accumulare povertà? Note sull report dell&#39;ISTAT &#34;La povertà in Italia 2014 [Accumulating poverty? Notes on the ISTAT Report “Poverty in Italy 2014”]&#34;</title>
      <link>/dissemination/filandristruffolino2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/filandristruffolino2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Published on &lt;em&gt;Il Menabó di Etica e Economia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proprietà della casa e riproduzione delle disuguaglianze nella Legge di Stabilità per il 2016. [Household tenure and reproducion of inequalities in the Stability Law for 2016].</title>
      <link>/dissemination/filandristruffolino2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/filandristruffolino2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Publishe on &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Menabò di Etica &amp;amp; Economia&lt;/em&gt;, eticaeconomia.it&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Traiettorie lavorative e salariali a inizio carriera in Italia. Un&#39;analisi longitudinale</title>
      <link>/publication/raitanostruffolino2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/raitanostruffolino2013/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working poor. Lavoratori con basso salario o occupati che vivono in famiglie povere? Un’analisi del fenomeno in Italia prima e dopo la crisi</title>
      <link>/publication/filandristruffolino2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/filandristruffolino2013/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
