<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Academic</title>
    <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heuristics for validation and visualization in Sequence Analysis</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_4_methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_4_methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.unibocconi.eu/raffaellapiccarreta/&#34;&gt;  Raffaella Piccarreta&lt;/a&gt; (Bocconi University, Milan)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publications in progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Piccarreta R., Struffolino E., &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/v7mj8/&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;Heuristics for validation in Sequence Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Piccarreta R., Struffolino E., &lt;em&gt;Enhancing fuzzy clusters’ interpretation  through visualization&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Family Demographic Processes and In-Work Poverty in Europe</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_2_oxber/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_2_oxber/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zachary-vanwinkle.com/&#34;&gt;  Zachary van Winkle&lt;/a&gt; (University of Oxford), Christiaan Monden (University of Oxford), Johannes Giesecke (Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project analyses the role of family demographic processes (leaving parental home, marriage, divorce, and parenthood) for the probability of being working poor and how it changes over the life course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publications in progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struffolino E., Van Winkle Z., Family formation and union dissolution and in-work poverty: Gender differences across the life course in comparative perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struffolino E., Van Winkle Z., Polizzi A., Family-demographic processes and in-work poverty: A systematic review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Van Winkle Z., Struffolino E., Parity and in-work poverty across the life course in comparative perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is funded by the &lt;em&gt;Oxford/Berlin Research Partnership - 2018&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender differences in early school leaving. Academic performance, family resources, and labor-market opportunities.</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_3_it_drop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_3_it_drop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.carloalberto.org/person/camilla-borgna/&#34;&gt;  Camilla Borgna&lt;/a&gt;  (Collegio Carlo Alberto, Turin)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the rising skill demands of the labor market, early school leavers constitute a vulnerable group in contemporary societies: young people who do not hold any kind of upper-secondary qualification tend to experience difficulties in transitioning to the first job and in later labor market integration. Early school leaving is also connected to other negative outcomes such as poor health and lack of civic and political participation. From a policy perspective, early school leaving can therefore be considered a “new social risk”, as recognized by the EU strategy for growth for which the reduction of early school leaving to less than 10% is one of the main five targets to be met until the year 2020.
Not only is early school leaving connected to negative labor market outcomes, but it also tends to hit the social groups that are most vulnerable in terms of labor market integration: children with learning difficulties, coming from socio-economically disadvantaged families or who have access to limited educational resources. Hence, early school leaving exacerbates social inequalities.
When it comes to gender, however, the definition of a vulnerable group may prove elusive, because while women still face labor market disadvantages in most industrialized societies, in terms of educational attainment they have caught up to men and, in many countries, even overtaken them.
Together with Portugal and Spain, Italy is one of the EU countries with the greatest proportion of early school leavers. In this country, early school leaving has been steadily declining since the 1990s, when it reached percentages of 30% or more. However, as of today still 15% of young Italians leave education and training before completing the upper-secondary cycle. This phenomenon is therefore alarming, especially if we consider the increasing difficulties that Italian youth is facing in labor-market entry: it suffices to say that as of 2015 the youth unemployment rate reached 40%.
Moreover, in Italy, gender disparities are particularly strong: on the one hand, women’s participation to the labor market is very low and, even among the young cohorts, the women who work are more likely than men to have atypical and poorly-paid jobs. On the other hand, the gender gap is reversed when it comes to education: young women outnumber men by three to two among tertiary graduates and boys are vastly overrepresented among the pupils who do not reach a basic level of competences in core subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publications in progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struffolino E., Borgna C., &lt;em&gt;Who is really left behind? Gender differences in the school-to-work transition of
low-skilled youth in Italy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Borgna, C., Struffolino E., &lt;em&gt;Tempi difficili. Le condizioni occupazionali degli early school
leavers in Italia prima e dopo la crisi&lt;/em&gt; [Hard times. Labor-market outcomes of early school leavers in Italy
before and after the crisis]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The stratification of contraceptive use at first intercourse in Italy, 1950-2006</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_5_contraception/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_5_contraception/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://hannahzagel.com/&#34;&gt;  Hannah Zagel&lt;/a&gt; (Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous research finds contraceptive use to be stratified both by social background and by gender. Analysing data from the “Survey on Italians’ Sexual Behavior” (2006), our study is the first to study these links in Italy. Looking at changes in contraceptive use at first intercourse before and after liberalization of family planning institutions in Italy, we find no difference by social background in the restrictive regulation period, but difference for young men in the liberal period. The probability of contraceptive use occurred for both young men and women, but women remain less likely to use contraception than their male counterparts even after liberalization. For studying the role of specific institutions, we included macro-level indicators for access to and information on contraception.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lone parenthood - Family and labor market dynamics in a life course perspective</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_6_loneparents/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/project/project_6_loneparents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the research group &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lone parenthood, vulnerability, and resources&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; at NCCR-LIVES &amp;ldquo;Overcoming vulnerability. A life-course perspective&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; (University of Lausanne).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outreach of publications related to this project&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;FORS (2019), &lt;a href=&#34;https://forscenter.ch/wp-content/uploads/2019/08/brochureannipsm_web.pdf&#34;&gt; How healthy are single mothers living in Switzerland?&lt;/a&gt; in &amp;ldquo;The achievements of the Swiss Household Panel. 20 years - Where did we come from and where will we go&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struffolino E., Bernardi L., Voorpostel M. (2016), &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.skbf-csre.ch/pdf/18067.pdf&#34;&gt; Selbstberichteter Gesundheitszustand, Erwerbstatus und Bildungsniveau alleinerziehender Mütter&lt;/a&gt;, SKBF - Schweizerische Koordinationsstelle für Bildungsforschung, ISSN 1013-6258&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struffolino E. (2016), &lt;a href=&#34;https://bibliothek.wzb.eu/artikel/2016/f-20082.pdf&#34;&gt; Mehrfach benachteiligt. Wie Bildung, Job und Einkommen die Gesundheit alleinerziehender Mütter in der Schweiz prägen&lt;/a&gt;, in “Familie 2016. Arbeit, Gesundheit und Partnerschaft im Kontext” WZB-Mitteilungen Nr. 153.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struffolino, E. (2016), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schattenblick.de/infopool/sozial/fakten/ssffo150.html&gt; &amp;ldquo;Mehrfach benachteiligt. Wie Bildung, Job und Einkommen die Gesundheit alleinerziehender Mütter in der Schweiz prägen”&lt;/a&gt;, Elektronische Zeitung, Schattenblick.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struffolino E., Bernardi L. (2016), &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/en/home/news/whats-new.assetdetail.350454.html&#34;&gt; One-parent households in Switzerland. Continuity and change over time&lt;/a&gt;, in Demos - Demographic information, ”Family, migration” - No. 1 June 2016. Neuchâtel. Swiss Federal Statistical Office.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
