<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Datacodes | Emanuela Struffolino</title>
    <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Datacodes</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Datacodes</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systematic review on family demographic processes and in-work poverty</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data2_iwpsysreview/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data2_iwpsysreview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Version 2.0.0. WZB Berlin Social Science Center. Dataset&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This archive includes all data compiled in the course of a systematic review on the association between family demographic processes and in-work poverty that represents the empirical material used in the paper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polizzi, Struffolino, Van Winkle. 2022. Family demographic processes and in-work poverty: A systematic review, Advances in Life Course Research, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.alcr.2022.100462&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.alcr.2022.100462&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article reviews ever published quantitative evidence on in-work poverty and family demographic processes in OECD and EU-28 countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this systematic review, we first provide a quantitative review of results from analyses that estimated the association between in-work poverty and parental home leaving, union formation, marriage, parenthood, and dissolution of non-marital and marital unions. This allows us to formulate tentative conclusions about whether and in which direction family demographic processes are associated with in-work poverty. Second, we discuss in detail conceptual and methodological advances in in-work poverty research, that is analyses that deviated from the more conventional approaches adopted in the analyses selected for the quantitative review or that accounted for the interaction between family demographic processes and individual or context characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methods report provides detailed information on all files included in the archive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can donwload the data from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2041&#34;&gt; GESIS Repository SowiDataNet|datorium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or remarks on the data, please send an email to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:emanuela.struffolino@hu-berlin.de&#34;&gt;emanuela.struffolino@hu-berlin.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use the data, please cite&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polizzi, Antonino; Struffolino, Emanuela; van Winkle, Zachary (2020): Systematic review on family demographic processes and in-work poverty. Version 1.0.0. WZB Berlin Social Science Center. Dataset. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2041&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.7802/2041&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KOMPAKK Essential occupations in Germany during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data5_kompakk_essential/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data5_kompakk_essential/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The “KOMPAKK - Essential occupations in Germany during the Covid-19 pandemic” data provide federal state-specific information on occupations classified as critical infrastructures. The dataset was compiled from decrees issued by the German federal states in response to the COVID-19 pandemic between April 2020 and May 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can donwload the data  &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.gesis.org/sharing/#!Detail/10.7802/2283&#34;&gt; GESIS Repository SowiDataNet|datorium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or remarks on the data, please send an email to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:emanuela.struffolino@unimi.it&#34;&gt;emanuela.struffolino@unimi.it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use the data, please cite:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gädecke M., Struffolino E., Zagel H., Fasang A.F. (2021), KOMPAKK - Essential occupations in Germany during the COVID-19 pandemic. Version 1.0.0. SowiDataNet|datorium. Dataset - &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2283&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.7802/2283&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KOMPAKK index of occupations’ teleworkability in Germany</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data4_kompakk_telework/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data4_kompakk_telework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Telework”, “home office” and “work from home” have recently become very prominent working concepts due to social distancing regulations during the COVID-19 pandemic. According to a study by Kohlrausch and Zucco (2020), in Germany the share of people who mainly work from home has increased from about 4% before the pandemic to approx. 20% during the first wave of the pandemic. Furthermore, the share of workers who alternate between business and home office also increased. In this development, telework was not equally distributed across all occupational and social groups.
With the project “Household structures and economic risks in East and West Germany during the COVID-19 pandemic: compensation or accumulation? (KOMPAKK)” we define economic risks that people were exposed to due to the COVID-19 pandemic. We therefore calculate several risk factors based on survey data from 2017 and 2018.
As some occupations might be well executed from home while others are not, we created an index which reflects the possibility of working from home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can donwload the data  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2263&#34;&gt; GESIS Repository SowiDataNet|datorium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or remarks on the data, please send an email to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:emanuela.struffolino@hu-berlin.de&#34;&gt;emanuela.struffolino@hu-berlin.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use the data, please cite&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gädecke, Martin, Struffolino, Emanuela, Zagel, Hannah, Fasang, Anette (2021): KOMPAKK index of occupations’ teleworkability in Germany. SowiDataNet|datorium - GESIS Data Archive, Cologne. Version 1.0.0. Dataset. DOI:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2263&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.7802/2263&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KOMPAKK index of economic sectors closure during the first wave of COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data3_kompakkclosure/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data3_kompakkclosure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The “KOMPAKK index of economic sectors closure during the first wave of COVID-19” is a dataset on the German federal state-specific sector closures compiled from the original state decrees (March/April 2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large and growing number of studies shows the severe social and economic consequences of the governmental measures introduced to reduce the spread of the Covid-19 virus in March and April 2020 in Germany. However, we still lack a systematic analysis of intra-German differences in regulations and outcomes. The German federalist system leaves decisions over the implementation of decrees by the federal government to the federal states. This meant that the 16 states issued individual decrees over economic sector closure and social distancing measures during the course of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We retrieved all decrees issued from 15.03.2020 to 17.04.2020 from the official website of each of the 16 federal states of Germany. To relate the economic sectors mentioned in the decrees to an international comparable system, we used the NACE rev. 2 classification (NACE = fr.: Nomenclature statistique des activités économiques dans la Communauté européenne).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can donwload the data from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.gesis.org/sharing/#!Detail/10.7802/2247&#34;&gt; GESIS Repository SowiDataNet|datorium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or remarks on the data, please send an email to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:emanuela.struffolino@hu-berlin.de&#34;&gt;emanuela.struffolino@hu-berlin.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use the data, please cite&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gädecke M., Zagel H., Struffolino E., Fasang A.F. (2021), KOMPAKK index of economic sectors closure
during the first wave of COVID-19, Version 1.0.0. SowiDataNet|datorium - Humboldt-University Berlin.
Dataset. - &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2247&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.7802/2247&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Family planning centres and doctors&#39;conscientious objection in Italy. Historical series by region - 1978-2017 - GESIS Repository SowiDataNet|datorium</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data1_familycenters/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data1_familycenters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Historical series of data from &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Relazione del Ministro della Salute sulla attuazione della legge contenente norme per la tutela sociale della maternitá e per l’interruzione volontaria di gravidanza - Legge 194 del 1978&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from 1978, the Ministry of Justice and the Ministry of Health have the duty to compile every year a report on the implementation of the law for the protection of maternity and for the voluntary termination of pregnancy (Law n. 194, paragraph 6, May 22nd) to the Parliament. Originally, this report (Relazione del Ministro della salute sulla attuazione della legge contenente norme per la tutela sociale della maternità e per l’interruzione volontaria di gravidanza - Legge 194/78).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reports were retrieved from the website &lt;a href=&#34;https://storia.camera.it/&#34;&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://storia.camera.it/&#34;&gt;https://storia.camera.it/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salute.gov.it/portale/home.html&#34;&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salute.gov.it/portale/home.html&#34;&gt;http://www.salute.gov.it/portale/home.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Information on objecting doctors and on the family planning centres are missing for the years 1978, 1979 and 1980. For the year 1981 only data for the family planning centres was available. Furthermore, there was no data for the year 1996.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We provide a ready-to-use excel file that contains information retrieved from the reports 1978-2017 on the regional level and on the NUTS-1 level on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number of gynaecologists [column Gynaecologists]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number of anaesthetists [column Anaesthetists]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number of paramedics [column Paramedics]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;percentage of gynaecologists who refused abortions due to a moral reason [column Objecting Gynaecologists]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;percentage of anaesthetists who refused abortions due to a moral reason [column Objecting Anaesthetists]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;percentage of paramedics who refused abortions due to a moral reason [column Objecting Paramedics]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number of public family planning centres in total [column Public Family Centres]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number of public family planning centres per 10.000 women between 15 to 49 year-old [column Public Family Centres [per 10k women aged 15-49]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;number of public family planning centres per 20.000 inhabitants [column Public Family Centres [per 20k inhabitants]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the number of private family planning centres [column Private Family Centres]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can donwload the data  &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.gesis.org/sharing/#!Detail/10.7802/1.2031&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or remarks on the data, please send an email to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:emanuela.struffolino@gmail.com&#34;&gt;emanuela.struffolino@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use the data, please cite&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gädecke, Martin; Struffolino, Emanuela; Zagel, Hannah (2020: Family planning centres and doctors&amp;rsquo; conscientious objection in Italy. Historical series by region. Version 1.0.0. WZB Berlin Social Science Center. Dataset.https://dx.doi.org/10.7802/1.2031&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
