<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Van Winkle Z. | Emanuela Struffolino</title>
    <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/authors/van-winkle-z./</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/authors/van-winkle-z./index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Van Winkle Z.</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Van Winkle Z.</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/authors/van-winkle-z./</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systematic review on family demographic processes and in-work poverty</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data2_iwpsysreview/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/datacode/data2_iwpsysreview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Version 2.0.0. WZB Berlin Social Science Center. Dataset&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This archive includes all data compiled in the course of a systematic review on the association between family demographic processes and in-work poverty that represents the empirical material used in the paper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polizzi, Struffolino, Van Winkle. 2022. Family demographic processes and in-work poverty: A systematic review, Advances in Life Course Research, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.alcr.2022.100462&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.alcr.2022.100462&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article reviews ever published quantitative evidence on in-work poverty and family demographic processes in OECD and EU-28 countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this systematic review, we first provide a quantitative review of results from analyses that estimated the association between in-work poverty and parental home leaving, union formation, marriage, parenthood, and dissolution of non-marital and marital unions. This allows us to formulate tentative conclusions about whether and in which direction family demographic processes are associated with in-work poverty. Second, we discuss in detail conceptual and methodological advances in in-work poverty research, that is analyses that deviated from the more conventional approaches adopted in the analyses selected for the quantitative review or that accounted for the interaction between family demographic processes and individual or context characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methods report provides detailed information on all files included in the archive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the data from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2366&#34;&gt; GESIS Repository SowiDataNet|datorium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or remarks on the data, please send an email to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:emanuela.struffolino@unimi.it&#34;&gt;emanuela.struffolino@unimi.it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use the data, please cite&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polizzi, Antonino; Struffolino, Emanuela; van Winkle, Zachary (2022): Systematic review on family demographic processes and in-work poverty. Version 2.0.0. WZB Berlin Social Science Center. Dataset. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2366&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.7802/2366&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Family demographic processes and in-work poverty. A systematic review</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/publication/2022spolizzietal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/publication/2022spolizzietal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender and race differences in pathways out of in-work poverty in the US</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/publication/2021struffolinovanwinkle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/publication/2021struffolinovanwinkle/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wege aus der Erwerbsarmut in den USA [Pathways out of in-work poverty in the US]</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Published in the &lt;em&gt;WZB-Mitteilungen Nr. 164&lt;/em&gt;, in the special issue &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Es wird eng. Ein Heft über die Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lavoratrici ma povere [Women who work but are poor]</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outreach of the article &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;When working isn&amp;rsquo;t enough. Family Demographic Process and In-Work Poverty across the Life Course in the United States&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; published on &lt;em&gt;InGenere.it - Dati, Politiche, Questioni di Genere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non basta il lavoro per scampare il rischio di povertà. Uno studio sugli Stati Uniti spiega come redditi bassi e transizioni familiari incidono sulla vita delle donne, soprattutto se non hanno la pelle bianca.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Working Isn’t Enough. Family Demographic Process and In-Work Poverty across the Life Course in the United States</title>
      <link>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/publication/2018vanwinklestruffolino2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emanuela-struffolino.com/publication/2018vanwinklestruffolino2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
