<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Van Winkle Z. | Emanuela Struffolino</title>
    <link>/authors/van-winkle-z./</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/van-winkle-z./index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Van Winkle Z.</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Van Winkle Z.</title>
      <link>/authors/van-winkle-z./</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systematic review on family demographic processes and in-work poverty</title>
      <link>/datacode/data2_iwpsysreview/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/datacode/data2_iwpsysreview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Version 1.0.0. WZB Berlin Social Science Center. Dataset&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This archive includes all data compiled in the course of a systematic review on the association between family demographic processes and in-work poverty that represents the empirical material used in the paper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polizzi, Struffolino, Van Winkle. 2020. &amp;ldquo;Family Demographic Processes and In-Work Poverty. A Systematic Review.&amp;rdquo; SocArXiv &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/zncaq&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/zncaq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The systematic review aims at locating empirical results on these associations within a common grid to summarize the findings with respect to five family demographic processes: parental home leaving, cohabitation, parenthood and subsequent births, union formation, and union dissolution. We concentrate on empirical studies on in-work poverty in OECD and EU-28 countries without any restriction on the year of publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first part of the systematic review, we provide a quantitative review of results from a comparative pool of cross-sectional analyses. In the second part of the systematic review, we perform a narrative review of the literature that pays special attention to recent research implementing a longitudinal design with household panel data and to alternative operationalizations of pivotal variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methods report provides detailed information on all files included in the archive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can donwload the data from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2041&#34;&gt; GESIS Repository SowiDataNet|datorium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or remarks on the data, please send an email to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:emanuela.struffolino@hu-berlin.de&#34;&gt;emanuela.struffolino@hu-berlin.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use the data, please cite&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polizzi, Antonino; Struffolino, Emanuela; van Winkle, Zachary (2020): Systematic review on family demographic processes and in-work poverty. Version 1.0.0. WZB Berlin Social Science Center. Dataset. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7802/2041&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.7802/2041&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wege aus der Erwerbsarmut in den USA [Pathways out of in-work poverty in the US]</title>
      <link>/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Published in the &lt;em&gt;WZB-Mitteilungen Nr. 164&lt;/em&gt;, in the special issue &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Es wird eng. Ein Heft über die Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lavoratrici ma povere [Women who work but are poor]</title>
      <link>/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/dissemination/struffolinovanwinkle2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outreach of the article &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;When working isn&amp;rsquo;t enough. Family Demographic Process and In-Work Poverty across the Life Course in the United States&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; published on &lt;em&gt;InGenere.it - Dati, Politiche, Questioni di Genere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non basta il lavoro per scampare il rischio di povertà. Uno studio sugli Stati Uniti spiega come redditi bassi e transizioni familiari incidono sulla vita delle donne, soprattutto se non hanno la pelle bianca.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Working Isn’t Enough. Family Demographic Process and In-Work Poverty across the Life Course in the United States</title>
      <link>/publication/2018vanwinklestruffolino2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2018vanwinklestruffolino2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
